One of the most important
[clears throat] wars of the last 50
years is one that we don't hear about
much. When in 1980, two of the Middle
East's most powerful countries, Iran and
Iraq, waged eight years of some of the
worst trench and chemical warfare since
World War I,
leaving both countries devastated. This
is the war that fractured the Middle
East into lines that still play out in
nearly every conflict there today. This
is the Iran-Iraq War. It's 1979 and Iran
is in the middle of a revolution. The
country is coming off of decades of
being ruled by the Shah. After years of
the Shah's corrupt autocratic rule, a
mass uprising violently overthrows him,
creating what becomes an Islamic
Republic
headed by an Ayatollah named Ruhollah
Khomeini. Khomeini and a group of Shia
religious scholars want to impose
fundamentalist rule on the country. They
establish a military force called the
Islamic Revolutionary Guard, which is
meant to protect their hold on the
revolution and to suppress the other
groups who helped overthrow the Shah.
The US is watching all of this in shock.
Their biggest ally in the region and a
major oil producer has just turned from
friend to fierce enemy.
But the biggest tremors of this
revolution are felt in the rest of the
Middle East. Iran sends out radio
broadcasts to Arab countries like Saudi
Arabia, Lebanon, Kuwait, and Iraq,
calling for people to rise up and
overthrow their own rulers. They're
trying to export their revolution to
their neighbors to gain new allies in
the region.
Neighboring leaders, most of them Sunni
Muslim, don't like this. Saudi Arabia's
king fears being overthrown just like
the Shah was. And in Iraq, Saddam
Hussein sees this Shia religious
revolution on his eastern border and
worries that the Shia majority that he
rules over will rise up against him,
too. But he also sees this as an
opportunity. The Iranian revolution has
left the country weak and fractured.
Khomeini and his revolutionary guard are
still fighting other political factions
for control. The Iranian military, which
used to be funded and trained by the
United States, is now weak. Its leaders
having been jailed or executed after the
revolution. So in September of 1980,
Saddam Hussein decides to prepare 10,000
Iraqi troops to cross the border to
invade Iran.
What's about to happen here isn't just
the start of a new war.
Saddam is kicking off a dynamic that
will dominate the Middle East for more
than 40 years.
>> [music]
>> The fight between revolutionary change
and status quo power.